okay it's cohort four and July 25th and
we're the second discussion of chapter
three
so before we look at the questions is
there anything that like anyone just
wants to start anything about the
reading or anything
even maybe some recent uh
live stream or or course or anything or
just
what their reading is like now of
chapter three
yeah go for it
so I I was thinking about this idea of
synchronization between the inner model
and the outer model which another term
for that could be adaptation to the
environment
active adaptation modifying the
environment and building a model of the
environment but Bronwyn mentioned
personality disorders and one of the uh
features there these are very fuzzy
Constructors being stuck in maladaptive
patterns that don't really fit the
environment and person is unable to
change them thus their energies uh they
swim in free energy so to speak and they
suffer and there's negative effect that
is present all the time I I do think
that these models are a little too
straight and narrow to account for
Psychopathology and I do think trying to
explain something like that with sort of
a a need formula is is just not ready
yet I mean I I think that these are not
doing it justice because you know uh
people exist who spend decades in
maladaptive behavior and they don't
uh do much about it to get better so I I
just find it that you know when when we
dictated and say this is the law this is
the first principle and this is how the
living thing does it bacteria perhaps
but in a person with like malignant
narcissism no
they don't
yeah it's a really good uh
question like what is the role of the
math in the science what's the role of
the science
quote science what's the role of the
math in the science
how just broadly extrapolative is it in
its interpretation
um and then what's the role of just any
any how is how is a math and science
mobilized
with personality
what does a principle matter in the
specific
what does a specific matter for a
principal
those are all huge questions
I think you'd be interested in a
cybernetic Big Five Theory they have a
few papers where they connected to free
energy principle to try to go at
different psychopathologies and try to
see how you can like think of in a
cybernetic perspective it might be
something you might be interested in
I'm familiar with the big five Theory
it's also statistics based I'm a
clinical psychologist and I think it's
uh has nothing to do with personality
disorders I think it's again trying to
uh uh quantize
but but still you know we're going for
mathematics trying to Define I mean it
would be good to to bring somebody in
the room who has a borderline
personality disorder and try to apply
that theory onto them they're
predictably unpredictable there's
something missing like I don't know
field Theory or Chaos Theory framework
it's just it it it uh it doesn't match
my empirical data of interacting with
his patients on a daily basis you know
and it doesn't come from papers it comes
from seeing what they do in life over
and over and over again it doesn't work
they still do it so uh
yeah one way I I I might kind of ask
this would be the personality traits are
more about the
um characteristics of the paths in a
cognitive model so it's like certain
type of Dynamics
in the map not the territory then in the
you know maybe a clinical setting first
off it's engagement directly rather than
engagement with the model
and also there's perhaps less of a focus
on just like
um in the in the short term about just
um population scale patterns and maybe
more emphasis on a person's action
patterns
and so then how can these two
sides kind of support each other in an
applied cognitive science
rather than like disengaging
[Music]
characteristics and uh cbtf cbft
uh and cybernetic Big Five Theory as
like another layered uh outside of just
traits
what was the name of the thing outside
of traits uh characteristic adaptations
oh yeah also anyone of course can always
be just clicking on the cursor and
following and taking notes
like people can have things just it's
all good if people want to to discuss or
just filling in other angles
but thanks everybody who has shared
any other
thoughts before we look at any of the
questions there could be anything
um
actually yeah it just as a brief
follow-up to the preceding conversation
I was just curious if anyone
finds interest in the notion of like
hyper precise priors I see that come up
very frequently in uh applications of
active inference to Psychopathology and
um I think basically the idea that
there's a like a very strong belief that
a certain model is correct to where it
kind of skews and coming
um you know sensory information and it
kind of continues
um to to impact future actions
um despite like disconfirmatory sensory
evidence I mean I I'm just in response
to the earlier conversation I found I've
found that to be really interesting and
I thought it dovetailed really nicely
with with studying Psychopathology
actually
yeah I I think it matches well to
something like delusion because if I
believe firmly that neighbor walks in my
house and changes the furniture when I
am outside then and it doesn't get uh
updated based on me calling the police
and calling you know installing cameras
then that sort of hyper precise priors
exactly
but I I do think that again trying to
stretch these approach to different
kinds of Psychopathology like as I've
mentioned say personality disorders
right
so a lot of personality disorders are uh
related to early experiences where the
child or adolescent try to adapt to the
environment which is very difficult to
survive it emotionally and they've
developed some habits that were not
solutions back then but there's nothing
better that was available to them and
they carried it through into adulthood
so uh for example you know a child often
in a divorce of parents ends up thinking
that he is the reason why they're
divorcing they end up internalizing
distress and saying I'm the guilty party
and then they get in trouble because if
I'm in trouble then maybe these two
Knuckleheads will get together and then
you see an adult patient Psychotherapy
in their 30s that apologize every
session for everything you know and
that's an example kind of and it's not
necessarily I mean it has a completely
different flavor from delusion and I
don't think the language is hyper
precise priority is sufficient to
distinguish between the two there's
qualitative differences uh and so I
guess that more stuff is needed to
describe the difference of it
what about something like uh obsessed
impulsive disorder uh where you could
think of it as a from like an ecological
psychological perspective as uh
a low tolerance for
affordances so yeah low tolerance for
uncertainty basically
um
that that would not do it justice that
would be a very simplistic approach to
OCD because there's different subtypes
people who do washing and check-in are
very different from borders
so
uh uh you could have people dysregulated
and people were just regulated childhood
OC there's a lot of it all together this
is an example of trying to you know uh
fit something very heterogeneic complex
into a simple formula and just saying oh
we got this cool Theory let's just
explain OCD with it no I mean I think if
we want to do the OCD Justice we need to
start with a lit review go to PubMed and
read all the theories about OCD genetic
influence you know environmental
influence uh you know chemistry
everything else put it all together and
then we should do it so this approach
from first principles to something as
complex as
uh it's almost Farr is a psychiatrist
uh Colonel friston is a psychiatrist a
lot of people who aren't they want to
just you know schlep a formula to OCD
and it just it doesn't work
well again what what is really the role
of a of a specific model
uh
construction of those models is usually
not uh utilized as a full account
but maybe in it it can seem that way or
be used that way in certain settings
like to guide action
um
and then also like
one good thing about generative modeling
is that it allows
really specific discussion of what has
and hasn't been specifically modeled so
first principle is just because
something feels like consilience in
one's own mind does not equate to an
explanation let alone useful in the
world
so
then there can be a discussion of like
okay what um sensory modalities and
enteroceptive modalities are taking into
account and what how's childhood you
know in this specific model of these
people who have ocds like oh there's no
generative model well we have chapter
six we have chapter nine
you can build the model but definitely
if it's just speculation about what
inclusion or exclusion of variables
you're just like kind of casually
curious about or professionally curious
about it's all speculative
so I think that kind of supports a more
bright line because then people can just
spitball a little more broadly
structurally
which everyone's gonna have some
expertise in some area but then also
it's clear like when someone's not
referencing a specific generative model
it's just a pure hypothetical so how
would uh what what um what would a
hypothetical linear regression account
for nothing
so what would a hypothetical cognitive
model account for well maybe something
but doesn't have to
so I have a question is this more of an
issue with how we're classifying
psychopathologies or is this as in like
each classification is too broad perhaps
and we need to be more specific maybe
and because maybe like the same like you
were saying like there's many different
types of obsessive-compulsive disorder
so maybe the ones that pertain to uh a
low tolerance for uncertainty
would need its own specific
classification
versus other ones that are different
yeah
which is a question there
there's many issues there one is you
know we apply mathematical apparatus to
another field we're trying to either or
cybernetic theories or something else
and it doesn't always work for example
in Psychology there's something called
ambivalence which is hating and loving
the person at the same time that concept
violates the logic of Aristotle and all
of mathematics is based on Aristotle and
logic so there you go you can't use the
absolutely fundamental framework while
you're trying to use something more
sophisticated like classifications and
whatnot and there's many critiques of
DSM classifications as the
declassifications but the important
thing is the construct is complex and
then you know before trying to model it
or explain it we should study the
existing literature and and go from
there because otherwise we are trying to
model our fantasy of OCD and what sort
of the the Practical reality of OCD that
is you know like uh sadly it's it's uh
still very bad like schizophrenia we
know about 14 possible causal factors
but there is no coherent fear of
schizophrenia that everybody exists on
nor depression it's the oldest condition
in the history of medicine but there is
no integrated theory of depression still
it doesn't exist
and so this active inference is one of
the attempts to do that but it still
falls short like if you use active
inference and you try to explain
everything from autism to I don't know
motor disorders
it doesn't fit it doesn't capture the
the core of autism it just it it it uh
it seems to fit you have this resonance
you're like oh that's cool I think I've
explained it but if you actually see
people with Autism you see that you're
explaining something else I mean because
the core of autism is mentalization
deficits so uh I
I don't know if it's a good answer but
it's a it's a very messy field it's very
different mathematics is very kind of
you either proven theorem it's either
true or false
in political psychics and there are
different things
yeah
that's why uh modeling work is part of
an integrated
scientifically plural framework
I need to do both oh just just it's it's
a suit it's a super over fit
like it's always about reading a monks
in between the citations and everything
else it's not about one paper one
experiment one data set it's always
about being explicit about the uh
interpretation and how the researchers
model was made and so if somebody shows
up talking to you
um with a lot of personal experience and
or a lot of meta-analysis I'm sure
that's a productive conversation
also can be productive
um someone who might not be aware of
some of those complexities but yeah
that's also there's also just like these
are it's always like active inference or
is this about just like any kind of
modeling
numerical or statistical modeling
because someone could also make I I
believe in identical we're not linear
regressions our health records aren't
linear regressions that's not the body
that's not decision making it's just
linear regression so Decades of
insurance being calculated that way for
example so if that ends up using
cognitive modeling that that's kind of
the gray Zone slash question
is what is that kind of cognitive
digital twin
not just the accumulation of information
from a privacy perspective
but that kind of like more decision
making
representation which of course is still
just map and not territory
but that's a different area
just one kind of modern connection I
don't know do people have any thoughts
on that
or how this relates to
um different machine learning like
how does it relate to machine learning
or what's happening right now with with
synthetic intelligence
um well
I know that uh
but it seems like self-attention
mechanisms are also trying to minimize
perplexity and there was this recent
paper that they're using called like
evolutionary Transformer architectures
where uh they basically add like an
evolutionary block to it which allows it
to so you have multiple sort of models
and they're also all trying to minimize
perplexity
um
and then I know like GPT the latest with
GPT was they it was like leaked that
they're using
um
they're using a
it's called a mixture of experts or
yeah basically like a similar type of
algorithms to just find what comes up
with the best sort of output among many
different models so I just thought
that's kind of similar to like some
things that were mentioned in active
inference especially this chapter
yeah that's one great connection also
with Collective behavior and evolution
and active but also attention I know
Holly and uh others have have kind of
thought about this or or considered a
little bit like attention
mechanisms first off attention is just
one of a huge variety of cognitive
mechanisms
anticipation expectation attention
so
um this is we can think about the
regimes of attention which is a concept
from the cultural work
with in cultured patterns regimes of
attention
uh to sensory into different things and
so
there could be a Transformer with a real
cognitive model
explicit semantically interpretable
active
figure 4.3 type cognitive model here's
the explicit attention function
for example and that and that there's a
lot more say in that area
but that's for those who are interested
I feel like that's a cool you know thing
to look into
any other chapter three thought or we
can go to the questions
all right everyone can can vote or just
uh
also open the question
all right
note that the resulting preferred course
of action or policy is directly
measurable in experimental settings
whereas a value function or prior belief
needs to be inferred and hence is more
indirect if not tautological measure
I'm not sure how or why the measure
might be tautological in the case where
the value function needs to be inferred
what is the tautology here
anyone have a thought on that
all right well I I I am not exactly sure
but
we can contrast reward learning with
active inference type generative
modeling so reward learning you're going
to assign some utility or value to
different states and then pursue
rewarding States like different chess
pieces get a value and then you want to
maximize that expected value
that's the imperative for selecting
different actions
then inactive
action is going to be selected based
upon it being the most
uh basically
it depends on the kind of agent because
different agents have different kind of
relationship with the future they're
simple agents or just
um kind of inert
or have deterministic action policy but
then there's the whole open-endedness of
cognitive systems so
um
they act to learn but they also act to
realize their preferred uh their
preferences about sensation
but however you look at their behavior
whatever you think about their behavior
whatever you propose as as guiding their
behavior
it is what is directly measurable in
experimental settings
which is shown in figure 9.2
oh 9.1
which we talked about actually in the um
other cohort earlier today
so we're talking about what we present
as stimuli and what we observe as
Behavior
so that's what this modeling approach is
Tethered upon that
setting where it's being a cognitive
model is being projected
in contrast if you propose some second
order function about the behavior like
well it likes being in the light not
because it expects to be the light and
that's the most likely thing but because
light is rewarding and so then it's
going to pursue reward
you've basically proposed
an ad hoc
potentially principled
but at the very least indirect
and possibly just self
describing
something that isn't this though
maybe there's some specific case but it
seems pretty vague
I mean anyone else think about the
tautology or
I sort of uh
just took that that quote as referring
to like uh so preferences
pardon me I'm still to kind of trying to
wrap my head around this like like
you're already starting with like a set
of preferences I suppose that you're c
um Matrix right and um
so there's the tautological aspect is
that I suppose whenever you're modeling
you always have to start
with some kind of C like we it's it's as
if it's saying that active inference Is
Not An Origin story it's just like we're
already there and so like there's no
explanation for the starting point we
can only measure what maybe results
following after our priors are already
defined something along those lines
nice that's a great thought
um
what there's a few ways to look at it
one one on the more formal side
is like
if we think about things that don't plan
they're going to be amongst other things
like that just the same and all like
diffusing particles
so like they have no preferred state in
the gas box
um so they're they're like they're
behaving like just kind of like
classically from experimental
perspective or like according to
thermodynamic equilibrium whereas
systems that have an attracting set
homeostasis
or
um acting with the c to kind of anchor
the attracting set
without any pragmatic value policy
selection there's just policies are
driven by pure epistemic which in
abstracted settings maybe on optimal
situation
but for embodied settings that's not
the general principle
so that's why there's those two
pragmatic and epistemic
which helps
um
give a lot of degrees of freedom because
this is a value that's calculated for
the specific model that somebody
constructs like in chapter six so it
can't be just generically said like well
the free energy of an estimate goes down
when it gets a seed it's like
it's it's way way speculative to say
before having like the specific kind of
model that's even being discussed
so and it's just it's explicitly what is
being
um the attracting set itself
not a proposed second order
variable
just one possibility
but under another approach is like that
is like backs like is it about modeling
or is it about active inferences like
okay what other what other approach
can be taken in this setting is this not
a worthy setting or like is there
another way to approach this
and what would that what would that kind
of a variable or what would that model
be
so it doesn't have to be all only every
[Music]
model
but that's kind of the the golden Hammer
Golden Nail or whatever
um
now that can be a simplifying
cognitive heuristic
which has all the benefits and
trade-offs of any cognitive system
engaging in a similar heuristic
but we're in the textbook group so we
can like learn and like scrutinize it or
like use it in ways that that don't
necessarily make specific sense in any
given one person's
experience of using it
leaf blower
any other thoughts on this question
what are the minimal contents of the
model encoded within the internal states
of an activation
I'm presuming that
one a statistical model of the hidden
causes of a sensory data and two
preferences about the state the
generative model needs to be in order to
ontologically persist Through Time
I feel like one is specified in the
section but where in the generative
model are the preferred States located
who has any thought on this
so would this not be what they describe
as like the motion of the action States
as the
prediction of the preferred States as
well
I don't know if that's
that covers that aspect
okay
possibly
um
like in the actual person I think it
kind of
can you say the relationship again
yeah so in the book they describe uh how
the Markov blanket not only is
predicting uh
sensory straight States it's also
um
doing so for the action States as well
I don't know if I'm phrasing that
correctly
but
if I can find it
one equation based way to to look at
this
is so where in the generative model are
preferred States located
there the sea here
so they're used in the free expected
free energy calculation so if if we're
talking about a kind of of simple model
not a simple system but a simple model
where the cognitive states are just like
a pass-through or you know a divide by
two or you know there or it just is just
a noise so the action policy in the
sensor are uncorrelated or uncausated or
anything like that like those are all
special cases but action policy
selectors which might be one step
selectors like instantaneous selectors
doesn't have to be an explicit planner
per se
um could be like a gradient based system
with bacteria
um pragmatic value is where preferences
are loaded
and pragmatic value rebates policies
accordingly to how
close you get
to the preference Vector slash variable
and how relevant that is in the behavior
is situational there's no generic answer
because the other component is about
epistemic gain
and so this is the the relationships
that's described in all those special
cases where this or that doesn't apply
so it's a totally good question
but it's a very you know
this is one of the key differences
between reward learning and active
inference in active inference the
preferences are explicit over sensory
States that's a relationship with
perceptual control theory
and it prevents overfitting because it's
about the incoming sensory data
predictive processing all of this
um there's no proposition of a reward
or utility function
what the agent is supposed to be doing
what our inference does procedurally
is just
these optimizations on the specific
proposed generative models
so first principle may do last work
generically
principle of least action people are not
always bringing this out to talk about
well this is why this plane did or
didn't fly
well this one was just following its
path of least action
so that's not an explanation or an
account
and I think that that's that code in
what you shared Lexi like sort of about
like about uh particulars and generics
and everything like that
so
first principle less specific work done
by the framework understanding the
framework
very prerequisite for modeling
understanding claims for for of course
just the joy and the fun everything like
that all the fun we have
um but understanding claims
like evaluating whether a given um usage
of the active inference ontology is like
valid
but then to do the applied modeling and
to understand it in the way like that a
graduate student type
might
then these are only kind of the enabling
pieces kind of like the L2
least um some squares minimization has a
relationship with linear modeling
but a more statistical student might
learn more about the underlying basis of
the linear regression
more empirical statistics student might
just apply data set modeling not go too
deep into the theory
just want to kind of provide some of
that context because like Kristen at all
have explicitly said this is for this
textbook that that were
gathering around like that it's a kind
of Masters student
again taped out for what it means and
there's always more variability like
within them between all these other
things but Master students
getting on the way to doing modeling
in this approach
based upon
reading the epistemic first half of the
book
I don't know what piece of course we're
having fun figuring it out
and then going into the modeling in
parallel
following along after the chapter six
with one's own kind of
specifications or just like Explorations
for different systems
some stubs of which we have and we can
collaboratively do too
but it's kind of just a general comment
because like if the philosophy is is
amazing it really is and people bring so
much to these discussions that that I'm
just so glad that that we have them and
everything like that
and a lot of it is is very
uh General and importance outside of
just active inference
which is really like uh in in the in the
textbook sense
like uh
comparatively
can be narrow
because it can feel like there's like a
lot of like things to get like rabbit
holes to get lost in and everything
Crags to fall into
but
I I I hope it throws a little context
hence just like regularly working with
material and just broader sketches
natural language that is consistent with
the equations but you know there's only
so much mystery in one's time in in life
with a mystery with the equations Alexi
yeah um thank you so much I mean I think
you described it beautifully I just
wanted to also comment that everything
we're talking about only applies for
systems just like when it says early in
the chapter that have an attracting set
this is fundamental quality of the
systems you describe on this figure 3-3
when they show a system that doesn't
have an attraction the system that does
have an attractor active versus
inference models talk about the ones
that do have an attraction okay kind of
converge right
uh and so I recently asked Carl via
email and he asked lanceland Acosta as
well what if they're attracting set
changes
for example if I sleep there's one
attraction set when I wake up there's
another tractor set and my entire system
bifurcates it evolves from let's say
periodic attractor to a strange
attraction
and they are working on that right now I
think this is a work in progress but
they will create a sort of a
hierarchical structure where the
attracting set itself is not kind of set
where you can describe and say that's
the attraction set but it can actually
change in and of itself and that's
that's a new interesting development
that may uh
that may help I don't know how people
feel about that
yeah that's awesome that sounds really
cool one one piece to bring in here this
is Axel Constance like
extremely
um kind of uh girdle Escher Bach
type
uh description of fep which kind of just
had to be said
but he he laid it down
and
the simple point I'm making this paper
is that the free energy principle is not
concerned with the sufficient conditions
of existence
but rather
with what must have been the case given
that you exist it's not about
figuring out what it takes to be alive
it's about figuring out what took you
there
that's just so deep and I think it it
gives a difference
accounts for a lot of settings just like
the surprisal versus reward
does
that um
now that that in place I don't know
exactly how they're related here because
maybe this could be taken you know but
it's like saying we're making a
measurement theory for measurable
objects
we have the blur so we know when there's
no signal that's just noise
that's going to be because that's the
Baseline informationally
and then we're going to have a theory of
measurements an analytic framework for
measurements cognitive measurements
observables and unobservables
um
a four measurable systems
or if you do a hypothetical it doesn't
have to be like an Adaptive system
so that's what's fun in the textbook
group is like we can imagine just like
okay let's just imagine that the
external state is just
alternating between two states
it's just like I mean it's great to
really wonder about these um really
contemporary examples and everything
like that but like
pedagogically
a lot of these existentials are
non-relevant it's good to keep them in
mind because I think a lot of the the
technical part like people can study and
um and the math learning group and
hopefully like it's you know
there could be good math discussions but
this is like I'll bring so much of the
broader context in
what everyone shares but because the the
math is not a metaphysic
and this
inversion of
um
of uh conditioning
like most people if they think about
um a theory of everything they're going
to think about it like from a sort of
material up
like how things came to be
versus
um so versus
at least
the measuring or modeling framework for
Signal versus noise
which does a less slash different work
per se than the than the um the accounts
of how something like comes to exist
because different mechanisms for things
coming to exist
they might have from it for a given
generative model
like they might have similar or
different Dynamics
but the model is not gonna like I think
here to um JF classier at The Institute
in his work with the uh symbolic active
inference
robotics
and about how we can have different
implementation architectures that can be
modeled
from a behavior like from an active
inference Behavior Uh perspective
but this doesn't mean that everything
has to be like running this exact
statistical model as a kernel
that's like figure 4.3 is like super
schematic
extremely it's like it's it's not a
claim about a system it's just super
evocative about the kind of structure
that can be expressed
for in the most minimal
way
and then there's a lot there's a lot
more to do and everything but
that's why it gets kept it keeps on
getting returned to
because it helps give a first pass
Separation on like priors
sends to Hidden as hidden state to
sensing
World model
and action model
so these are some of the essential
features of of
as it turns out a nerd and sentient
creatures
but this is not like
yeah
I hope that's not too too contextual but
just want to clarify because I I can I
can imagine slash C that that
what the equations do is a primary
concern slash awareness
and uh so so I think that it's very
um worthwhile for people who want to
continue like learning and thinking
about it like
just
um sharing their perspectives on
what these maths actually do
because then it's just parallel streams
where one is just like like
now I don't know just what do people
think about that or or how do we really
connect up even just in these short
discussions
some of these mathematical details which
are kind of just like
just defined as true essentially
and all these other systems of Interest
since like ways of knowing that we all
are interested in
um
I hope I'm not too like far afield from
the way that things are being framed a
moment ago but um I mean as far as
something like uh simultaneously or
simultaneous like attractor sets that
might be competing with one another for
example
um and the idea of like you know you
have a series of preferences
um I've I've not had too much trouble
wrapping my mind around the idea that
you can have you know competing uh
tractor States or competing preferences
if you need to use the restroom and
you're hungry and you're very sleepy all
at the same time and so we have these
models that you know whether it be the
discrete version or the continuous
version they all happen in time and they
all involve like policy selection over
time so for example if I decide oh like
you know it's I'm very tired but it's
only 2 p.m I could take a short nap and
then I could get up and you know have a
snack and use the restroom whatever I
need to do but you can plan things out
over time and and as far as the
relationship between that and the math
goes
um like we have that nice like expected
free energy equals you know epistemic
value the real you know the combination
of the epistemic value and the pragmatic
value and so your C's your preferences
are only in
um pragmatic value as you mentioned
earlier Daniel
so whenever you aren't sure what to do
you have these competing preferences
like there's a almost like a uniform
probability between them like which one
is going to win out I'm not sure you
would rely upon doing actions that
involve gaining more epistemic value
like oh well I'm going to have to spend
a moment like planning and what makes
the most sense here can I come up with a
plan that helps me to like resolve some
of this uncertainty going forward and do
that and you know um or maybe you have a
certain belief that one of these things
is just incredibly important and so you
you stick with that one in the first
place or maybe you become conflicted not
to not to backtrack but on the topic of
Psychopathology I'd be interested to see
someone just attempting to model
decision making and planning and so on
in the context of someone who might have
you know some kind of anxiety disorder
for example or in fact like maybe you
have an additional Merchant behavior
that is spending you know five to ten
minutes or maybe a few hours like
ruminating having issues about what to
decide upon I read up I'll try to find
it but I find an interesting paper that
tries to get at you know modeling uh
rumination in that kind of context so
that those are all my comments here on
the idea of like competing preferences
and relationship to the mathematics oh
yeah
nice thank you
one other
um aspect uh to kind of so whether it's
the visual form which is describing the
sparesity of the base graph like which
nodes
connect to wish knows this is this is
kind of like the skeleton of
the model generative model
this is where the time concept is
embedded this is where the action
concept is embedded sense making concept
prior concept
so it could be viewed this way and then
the equations are describing like
statistical operations on that and and
that's why uh
but
whatever structures proposed
it to be applicable to any actual system
it's a parameterized
data set
specific model specific data set
like saying let's um imagine that uh
childhood just imagine the childhood
experience one two and three are
associated with um with cybernetic B5 or
DSM such such and such just imagine that
they're that case so what do you think
about this being the case this one's
associated with that
it's like well I don't know you haven't
specified the model or applied it to a
data set but it's like oh yeah but you
can like see that that would be a really
important thing right
it's like okay perhaps but that's a
purely verbal argument that's what I was
referring to earlier as just speculative
that can be an intuition pump and I
believe serve a lot of other functions
and and communication functions and
other features
but um that is not what a scientific
account consists of
which is a much slower term
um pluralistic
um synthesis
not not to be like too old school on
that topic but I think it helps enable
open-ended discourse which I believe is
important and when people watch so many
different backgrounds and and and
familiarities
that that of course everyone's going to
be like thinking and saying things that
we would not think and say because we
come from so many backgrounds but just
what happens in a discussion around a
textbook is not
um is not it's in a Continuum of
communication but it's not of the type
of a scientific account
ajith
yeah so
um I have a question about something
else but
uh just kind of the idea that like our
behavior is governed by a principle of
least action
so how does this affect like
um assumptions of like measurement
Independence so like some experiments
uh for example like the one they use to
sort of
even tests so I'm not my background
isn't physics so
um if anyone knows correct me if I'm
wrong but to test like
uh Bell's inequality there's an
assumption of measurement Independence
that like you can actually make
decisions and it's not actually affected
by sort of the environment or what's
going on uh and this is sort of a way to
actually like
make it so you can actually test certain
things and if you can assume measurement
Independence that kind of breaks science
there or a lot of people think it breaks
sort of science there so uh Concepts
like super determinism uh
is one that assumes that every sort of
like Behavior or action is something
that uh kind of is dependent on sort of
all the past States as well basically so
um yeah I was just wondering like I I
don't know exactly how like active
inference would play in that like does
this go against measurement Independence
if it is a principle of least action
because it's like going in the direction
like the most least effort basically
yeah there's a ton of areas I'm not
familiar with every single aspect there
this is as Toby Smith
um uh Sinclair Smith uh called it in his
recent dissertation which was uh live
stream 54 series
he called it
compositional cognitive cartography
we're talking about maps variational
free energy expected for energies are
properties of maps that are human
constructed and modeled hashtag John
Dewey all of this other pragmatism and
and threads that are brought in there's
nothing generic to say about free energy
or expected free energy except for the
truly generic active ontology type
Expressions so that's why we can like
open up and have a lot of richness with
the chapter six type discussion about
modeling because they're so far to go as
people are encouraged to do in the
textbook group
um and through time with just like
whether you're coding is that um this or
that I hope we can develop better uh
coding and all these other things
collaboratively anyone's welcome to do
this
a lot of these are questions about
specific model settings and um
there's a big Continuum between kind of
touching the theory and touching the
system
but that's the inclusion that we get to
cultivate with the right Niche if we can
create the right artifacts that support
people who are different understandings
because like there's a lot of threads
that were brought in relatively
um
early in terms of like the connection to
ecological psychology
and predictive coding some of these
things are are only finding any
empirical uh um support but with rapidly
expanding amounts since like 1999 with
kind of the classic round Ballard type
predictive coding
models
so not there any given communities like
acceptance of something matters or what
is in the literature because there's
kind of like the timelessness of the
ideas in a sense but
um
like
again I just there's a broad range
between the mathematical and the
engineering and all these other
perspectives
so it's very wide that's what makes it
wide open in terms of like creating like
well what about accounting from this
perspective
that's those are almost always good
directions to go if you're you know here
and curious
and uh what What's so fun is as people
continue to go deeper in their um work
that it it can go from like kind of
um
uh tautologies
um or or just just um just active
infantology
scaffolded to actually implement it
which brings us a lot of
um and and entails many codes of paint
and a lot of like Hands-On and working
with some of these questions that are
that we may have
surely the agent is a generous model
map territory
but then people sometimes do go beyond
and go into the ontological and and uh
but but that's that's definitely a
secondary
Claim about a system
one that might be merited or not but
it's a secondary claim so first
approximation we're just talking about
the modeling apparatus
that may describe something fundamental
in a given system
but also literally may not or just maybe
one of many things that
any other um
thoughts or questions people have
yeah well
a few more things from chapter three
and then into chapter four anyone who
has read it before Wanna Give a note on
chapter four
M Carl six
okay
any other questions or or we'll end
all right
all right thank you see you all next
time bye